(GATE BUZZING)
(PRISONERS CLAMORING
INDISTINCTLY)
(METAL CLINKING)
MAN: Yo. are you up?
Yeah.
Jax has got
the jump on you tomorrow.
Two bell.
I figure I owe you.
Yo. Did you hear
what I said?
RAY: I heard.
Thanks.
(GRUNTING)
(SCREAMING)
MALE GUARD: Everybody down now!
On the ground!
(SIREN WAILING)
You! Inmate! On the ground!
(DOGS BARKING) Down!
Get down!
GUARD 2: You heard him!
GUARD 1: On the fucking ground!
(DOOR BUZZES)
(RADIO CHATTER)
ROAG: You're up.
To your left.
On the line.
(GUARD CLEARS THROAT)
All right...
Step to the right.
(KEYPAD BEEPS)
(DOOR UNLOCKS)
Let's go.
Hands.
Enjoy.
(DOOR BUZZES)
(MUFFLED DISTANT VOICES)
Against the wall.
(DOOR BUZZES)
Let's go.
(BANGING ON DOOR)
GUARD: Lunchtime. inmate.
Eat your veggies.
(DOOR BUZZES)
There you go.
Hey. Roag!
Yeah?
Got the time?
Fuck you care?
You got a date?
No.
Maybe you got
a sister or a cousin?
Wanna get your head smashed?
No. not really.
It's five to 4:00.
Wise ass.
Hey. Fruitcake!
Let's go.
RAY: Two... Three... Four...
Five... Six... Seven...
Eight...
Nine...
Ten...
RAY: 290... 291...
292... 293...
294...
295... 296...
297... 298...
299... 300.
What the fuck...
Come on!
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
(SIREN BLARING)
ROAG: You okay?
I got everybody.
(SIREN WAILING)
(TELEPHONE RINGING)
What the fuck's going on?
MAN: We've got a fire.
gate two.
All prisoners
back to their cells.
Copy that.
What the fuck...
We got a runner!
Repeat. prisoner is running!
(SIREN BLARING)
Let's go. let's go!
(SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY)
Nice look.
Hush's idea.
Nice. right?
How was inside. boss man?
Inside's great.
Everyone's asking about you.
If you weren't out soon.
I'd be breaking into
that motherfucker
and pulling your ass out.
Only ex-con I know gets out.
wants to go back in.
I didn't say "wants."
I said I would.
There is a difference.
Don't spend it all
in one place.
WOMAN ON RADIO: We have an escape
from Bendwater Penitentiary.
(SIREN CHIRPS)
(TIRES SQUEAL)
(SIRENS APPROACHING)
Step out of the booth
with your hands in the air!
Showtime.
Put your hands
in the air! Now!
Get them up. now!
Hands in the air!
Put your hands on your head!
Interlock your fingers! Do not move!
Beautiful day.
(CHATTER ON RADIO)
(SIRENS BLARING)
What the hell is going on here?
Calm down. Warden.
I'm Lester Clark.
I'm the CEO of B&C Security.
You might have heard of us.
No?
All right. well... We're an
independent security company
hired by the Federal Bureau
of Prisons
to test the integrity of their maximum
security facilities nationwide.
This is Ray Breslin. He's my
partner and resident Houdini.
Warden.
For the last seven years.
Ray has been inserted into
every maximum incarceration
facility in the system.
He is there to ensure that
each and every one of them
is 100% escape-proof.
And apparently yours wasn't.
and he got out.
Ta-da. (CHUCKLES)
Okay. fine.
I suppose you're gonna
tell me how you did it?
Think he wants to know?
Doesn't seem like it.
Ray. you're on.
Warden.
let's start from the top.
RAY: Any break requires three
things. knowing the layout.
understanding the routine.
and help from outside or in.
If you know the layout.
the weak side is obvious.
In Bendwater's case.
it's the Secure Housing Unit.
The government expenditure was 17
million dollars building that facility.
It's state-of-the-art.
The only problem is. it's located
next to an unsecured fire garage.
First I needed to get inside.
so I made some enemies.
(GRUNTING)
Once inside. it was obvious
you were short-staffed.
Federal guidelines recommend
two guards are present
when transferring high risk inmates.
You only use one.
Knowing the guards' routine
was the next step.
Thirty seconds into my rec time.
my CO took a smoke break.
For seven minutes every day.
there were no eyes on me.
Two...
After I knew the routine. all
I had to do was pick the day
and arrange for a distraction at the
front gate for exactly 4:00 p.m.
But at this point. you were still
locked inside a steel box.
To get out.
you had to have a key code.
You have very
good chocolate milk.
See. the cartons contain a
thin layer of wax laminate.
Lay it over the keypad.
the impression will indicate
which four keys were pressed.
With the four keys.
it's just a numbers game
to identify
the correct sequence.
I just needed
to get to the keypad.
After I covered my tracks.
I had one minute to make it
to the fire response
shed before the team did.
I knew the guards
were still on the roof
doing what they do.
which is wasting time.
What the fuck are you saying?
And before you know it.
I'm right where I want to be.
(SIREN BLARING)
Just in time to catch my ride.
Then your men drove me
right off the grounds.
You have any questions?
Yeah. One.
What kind of man would choose to
spend most of his life in prison?
Don't take it personally.
Warden.
Over the years. Ray has broken
out of 14 of these institutions.
Some people have a talent
to paint. some to sing.
Me. I sing.
Ray Breslin. he possesses
a unique set of skills.
He is able to break out
of any prison designed by man.
So have you been good?
Yeah. You?
You a good boy inside?
Of course.
Okay... How did that
thing with that guy go?
What guy?
When I was going in.
you were about to
have dinner with
some guy. some bozo.
Oh. yeah. That bozo
ended before dessert.
Well. that's his loss.
Yeah.
They're all losers.
How many times
have I told you that?
You want to get something
to eat when we get back?
Is there a problem?
You're a horrible cook.
(CHUCKLES)
That's nice. Well. you can
complain in the morning.
Ouch.
Morning. sir.
How can I help you?
Oh. Mr. Breslin.
I'm so sorry. I'm Jules.
That's okay.
You're new here?
No. sir. I've been
here five months.
Five months?
Yes. sir.
What do you got for me?
Check it out.
That's good. Very smart.
Did you do this all by yourself?
I'm impressed. Genius.
You're smart. but...
Sorry. not smart enough.
(CHUCKLES)
Don't be bitter.
(INTERCOM BUZZING)
SECRETARY: Mr. Breslin. they're ready
for you in the conference room.
(EXHALES)
Morning. Les. Abby.
Jessica Mayer.
It's an honor to meet you.
Your work is the gold
standard in the field.
What you've accomplished
is remarkable.
(MOUTHS INAUDIBLY)
Thank you.
And you're here because...
She's Agency. Ray. As in...
Central Intelligence Agency.
You a spy?
Worse. I'm a lawyer.
Ray. hear her out. She's legit.
I called Langley myself.
Fine. I'll just listen.
Go ahead.
Mr. Breslin. after ending
"extraordinary rendition."
the Agency is looking for
alternate situations for
incarcerating the sort of people
who commit acts so despicable they're
best... Well. how can I put it?
Eliminated?
Disappeared. And we're
currently testing a prototype
to deal with people no
government wants on their books.
But first and foremost. the people
financing this need to know
these facilities
are escape-proof
before the whole system
goes online globally.
ABIGAIL: What she's really
saying is that none of this
is officially
sanctioned by anyone.
JESSICA: Close.
What I'm saying. Miss Ross.
is that these facilities are
privately funded and administered.
So the word "official"
does not really apply.
So if anything goes wrong.
nothing comes back to bite
you people in the ass.
Whoa!
This is not your concern.
Hey! I owe him.
I don't owe you.
My job is to make sure the
United States is safe and clean.
All right. can we just cut the
crap and call it like it is?
These institutions
are off the grid.
There are no trials.
there's no convictions.
These people
are just disappeared.
And you want him
to go in and test it?
Maybe it's time
for me to interject
into the conversation
that they have offered
double your standard fee. that's
five mil. right? In advance.
So you like this?
LESTER: Look. I'm a numbers guy.
You're the artist. Ray.
From a financial standpoint. I like it.
Yes. I like it very much.
JESSICA: Beyond the money.
Mr. Breslin.
the people that are
sent to this place
should not be allowed out
into the real world.
Every one of them is a potential
game changer. For the worse.
All right.
Guidelines?
The usual. Full work. Alias. Cover story.
Contact. Evac number. Right?
Well. the only difference is to fully
test the security of the system
it's essential that none of you
know the location
of the incarceration.
(SCOFFS)
Will that present a problem?
Yes. Yes. it would.
When do we start?
We just did.
You and your new identity will
be picked up from this location
by private contractors
24 hours from now.
(PEOPLE CLAMORING)
(DIXIELAND JAZZ MUSIC PLAYING)
ABIGAIL: I don't like this.
And you don't like her.
Um. don't flatter yourself.
We're going against
every protocol and guideline
that you yourself
have insisted on
every single time
that you've gone in.
And I don't like her.
You're right. There's nothing
to like about any of it.
Then why do it? Because
he's ambitious and greedy.
You say that like
it's a bad thing.
Profile.
ABIGAIL: Name. Anthony Portos.
Born Madrid.
Mother died when you were 13.
Raised by your
father in the U.S.
You were suspected of manufacturing
bombs that have been used
in a dozen political bombings
across Europe and South America
for the last 10 years.
Contact on site?
HUSH: Warden's name
is Roger Marsh.
Evacuation code?
3-1-0-2-7-5.
All right. Let's do it.
Tag him.
No. I don't need this.
Really.
HUSH: Yeah. you do.
It's non-negotiable.
You think I'm
letting you go in cold?
This gets old.
Man the fuck up.
Try it some time.
Sounds good. boss man.
Any time you want to retire...
I've been takin' notes.
I'm ready to step up.
Where am I gonna find another
techno-thug as gifted as you?
Freak of nature.
Yeah. very rare.
There you are. baby.
Transponder's good.
It's like having me
right on your shoulder.
Where else?
HUSH: Hey. don't forget
to write us. All right?
(BEEPING)
(GROANS)
Ah.
Shit!
(HORN BLARING)
(HELICOPTER WHIRRING)
(MAN GRUNTING)
Hold it!
(SCREAMING)
(SIREN BLARING)
Put him to sleep.
(GRUNTS)
(DOOR BUZZES)
(RADIO CHATTER)
(GRUNTS)
Prisoner 7458.
Anthony Portos.
Welcome to the International
Detainee Unit intake.
I'm Warden Hobbes.
Hobbes.
Where's Warden Marsh?
There is no Warden Marsh.
What. am I disoriented?
Is that it?
I guess that must be it.
And I didn't see a man killed
on a transport helicopter
and thrown out either. right?
Mr. Portos.
your intake is finished.
Wait!
My evacuation
code is 3-1-0-2-7-5.
Evacuation code?
Yes. Evacuation code.
Meaning you give me a number and you
walk out of here free as a bird?
No. I don't think so.
You're here now.
And you belong to me.
Your intake is finished.
(SNAPS FINGERS)
Wait...
I have an evacuation code!
Anything?
Getting a ghost bounce. same as yesterday.
I can't find him.
You ran a full diagnostic
on the system?
Twice.
Run it again.
(DOOR BUZZES)
GUARD: All prisoners
A-Block proceed to Babylon.
All prisoners A-Block
to proceed to Babylon.
Portos.
(GRUNTING)
(MAN SHOUTING
IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE)
Everybody's days are
numbered in Babylon!
(SHOUTING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE)
Babylon. death. death!
(LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
Hey!
(SPEAKING FOREIGN LANGUAGE)
Go make some friends.
You're gonna need them.
Assalam-alaikum.
Hey!
(BLOWS KISSES)
(GATE BUZZES)
(PRISONERS CLAMORING)
Stay down! Stay down!
(LAUGHING)
(ALL GROANING)
New fish. We own you!
(WINCING)
ROTTMAYER: Back off!
Last time.
Back away.
(GROANING)
Portos. Hmm.
Rottmayer.
Emil Rottmayer.
Really not much in a
hand-shaking mood right now.
Okay.
Your name.
The fourth Musketeer.
It's a good name.
Why are you in here?
Why do you care?
I used to work security for a
guy by the name of Manheim.
Victor Manheim.
Have you heard of the name?
Manheim. let me see... No.
He's a genius.
Really?
He has this habit
of taking money
from the rich
and giving it to the poor.
You've heard
that story before...
I've heard that story.
Yeah.
Now they're trying to find him.
But I'm not gonna help them.
Okay.
So fuck 'em!
Right. Fuck 'em.
Portos. don't get killed.
If you say so.
Last time they killed
a guy in here.
they let his body rot
for three days. Hmm.
Oh. and they canceled
the prison dance.
Wouldn't want
to fuck up the prom.
Morning. sir.
That's another
beautiful piece. sir.
You lied to me.
I lied to you?
I'm not sure what...
No. no.
You say nothing.
What am I supposed to tell the
client about the man you killed?
That he just jumped.
like you said?
This isn't a free-for-all. We're
paid to prevent him from jumping.
And I can't get proof
of life from a dead man.
So...
You will be docked
the entire price of the asset.
The entire price of the asset
equals a month of my pay.
Then you're lucky the man you
killed was not high value.
That is all. Drake.
(DOOR OPENS)
MAN: Allahu Akbar.
Allahu Akbar.
Hey. Portos! Look at this.
There's no sunrise. no sunset. but
still they pray all the time.
Don't you find
that interesting?
Not really.
You look like the kind of a guy
that finds things interesting.
You've done time before?
MAN: Allahu Akbar.
Why all the questions?
That's how I learn things.
You really ought
to study somebody else.
Portos!
What?
Need a favor?
The favor man.
For a man who is
not interested.
you're doing a lot of looking.
What do you need?
I need to get into
the isolation area.
No. you really don't.
Yeah. I really do.
Call it a favor.
Okay?
Okay.
Good. Ah!
(ALL CLAMORING)
That's a favor?
Sometimes favors hurt.
Really?
Come on.
Okay.
Let's see what you can do.
All right.
(CHUCKLING)
You hit like a vegetarian.
Do I? You can do
better than that.
Come on.
All right.
Let's see it.
Try this.
(GRUNTS)
Hurt?
That was good.
Look what's coming!
(BOTH GRUNTING)
Relax. It's pretend.
Guess boys will be boys.
That's enough.
(ALARM RINGING)
Ah!
HOBBES: Put them
in the box! Now!
You can thank me later.
(PANTING)
(WINCING)
ABIGAIL: They knew he was tagged.
Of course they knew. Who do
you think these guys are?
What do you think.
they're a bunch of
yahoos from one of
those BOP facilities?
This is the shadow world. These
guys. they invented this shit.
Why do you think
they pay us all that money?
Remember what
the guidelines were.
What the fuck are you talking about?
There are no guidelines.
Now. you call that CIA bitch.
Hush...
Motherfucker.
All right.
I'll make the call.
Abigail. you got to keep him
away from me. all right?
Give me your arm.
(PUMPING)
You'll live.
How does a doctor work
in a place like this?
Would you prefer
there wasn't a doctor here?
Where is "here"?
Hey. Doc. let's wrap it up.
(EXHALES)
Doc...
What did he ask you?
He...
Wanted to know
how his dehydration
compared
to the other detainees.
And what did you tell him?
I don't care.
That's what I told him.
Get him out of there.
Did you find what you were
looking for in the box?
MAN ON PA: All prisoners
back to their cells.
All prisoners
Who were you before you
came in here. Portos?
You're always watching the room.
always watching everything.
Are you asking
what I used to do?
Yeah.
I'll tell you.
but I need a little favor.
Fuck that.
All right. don't do it.
All right. I'm listening.
What's the favor this time?
I need a piece of metal.
about three inches wide.
Round. smooth.
Oh. no problem. I'll hit the Home
Depot. and I'll be right back. Okay?
If you get me
that piece of metal.
I might be able
to get you out of here.
Tell Hobbes I want to talk.
MAN ON PA: Interrogation.
ready for inmate.
Interrogation.
You've been here six
months now. Mr. Rottmayer.
So you know how this works.
Ten seconds.
(EXHALES)
Where is Victor Manheim?
You know. to many
people. he is a hero.
Nine seconds.
Do you have a pencil
and a piece of paper?
Eight seconds.
I could draw you a map.
Of what?
Where you could find him.
When I was a kid. I always
wanted to be an artist.
My God. you are pushing it.
Problem was. I had no talent.
(CHUCKLING) Six seconds.
I tried and I
tried and I tried...
Five...
Do you ever have dreams?
Four...
Or did you always want to be...
...this?
Two...
One...
Done.
Look. There.
I told you.
No talent.
The records indicate that you
are a highly intelligent man.
As such. I would have expected
you to see the situation
and understand it
for what it is.
In here. you have no control
over any part of your life.
except your breathing.
And you just
lost that privilege.
(SNAPS FINGERS) Get him down!
(PANTING)
(GURGLING)
Keep going.
Enough.
(CHOKING)
(SNAPS FINGERS)
What happened?
Nothing.
I'm still here.
Now it's your turn.
I break out of prisons
for a living.
For the past eight years.
I've been breaking out of facilities
for the Federal Bureau of Prisons.
I think Hobbes used my reports
to make this place unbreakable.
Someone wanted this place
tested. but it was a set-up.
They wanted to bury me. I don't
know who. but I'm gonna find out.
I need you to set up
another diversion.
What now?
You've got to go
back in the box.
No fucking way.
Want to get outta here?
Okay. I'll do it.
But if I don't
get out. I kill you.
Fair enough.
A successful breakout
depends on three things.
layout. routine. and help.
But they've taken those away.
For now.
There's something under the box.
I think it's a conduit.
If it is. how do you
know where it goes?
I don't.
But I'm gonna find out.
This is good.
It's disgusting.
RAY: The mind of a man confined works
differently than someone on the outside.
He sees things different.
The architecture is vertical.
The cell blocks. Babylon.
the box. the mess...
Everything's in large
vertical compartments.
Best guess is they
built out underground
in large natural
fissures and caves.
In a vertical structure. 70/30 says
whatever's under that box goes up.
If I can get in there.
follow where it goes.
Let's say you're right.
How do we cut metal?
We don't cut.
We don't cut at all.
This place is subterranean.
There's moisture in the air.
Whoever built this place should
have used aluminum rivets
to hold those panels down.
but they used steel.
Steel rusts over time.
We apply that. We'll concentrate
the heat to those rivets
and they'll expand
and snap right the fuck off.
Concentrated heat?
Yeah. from the piece
of metal you gave me.
You expose a toothpaste-polished
piece of metal to sunlight...
Or the lamps in the box. Right.
At a hundred degrees
centigrade.
steel expands .03
cubic centimeters
and those rivets are
gonna come right off.
What?
You don't look that smart.
You don't either.
RAY: So most prisons
are built around small towns.
No matter how remote. they need
supplies and a work force.
If I can get to the surface.
I'll know what it's going to take to
get over the wall. get out of here.
But first I'm gonna need
that diversion in the box.
How much time do you need?
Three to five minutes.
No problem.
Step back.
I know you.
You don't know shit.
you cunt-eater.
Now step back.
Oh. now I remember.
What?
Your mother. she was my
favorite whore in Marrakesh.
Man. she could polish a helmet!
(SHOUTING IN ARABIC)
(ALL CLAMORING)
(ALARM BEEPING)
Ah!
No!
Hey!
(PANTING)
(GRUNTS)
(KNOCKING)
Ah!
ROTTMAYER: You're killing me!
You're killing me!
Bringing up box four. sir.
(ROTTMAYER SCREAMING)
HOBBES: Now. what is he up to?
(SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
Hey! Shut the fuck up.
you German dog!
MAN: Master control.
please advise.
(SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
Just hold him till I get there.
MAN: I've got a camera
malfunction. box two.
MAN 2: Roger that.
Just reboot the system.
Shit!
(WATER FLOWING)
(ROTTMAYER YELLING)
JAVED: Shut the fuck up!
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
JAVED: Hey.
Rottmayer. shut up!
GUARD: Restrain
and drug him. sir?
Not yet.
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
Lights off. box four.
Now open it.
(GASPS)
Rough day. Mr. Rottmayer?
(SCREAMING)
(GRUNTING)
(INDISCERNIBLE CHATTER)
Let's get 'em.
Here's what you should know.
I don't care.
Sooner or later you will
tell me what I want to know.
It is inevitable.
Like dying.
But know this. there will come a
point where I don't give a shit
about you or whatever the fuck you
think you're doing right now.
So have a lovely day.
Mr. Rottmayer.
(SCREAMING)
(ALARM BLARING)
MAN ON PA: Emergency
personnel to level two.
Emergency personnel
to level two.
Report?
Valve breach on level two. sir.
Electrical malfunction.
(PANTING)
Sir?
Get the assets out of there.
Open up!
Open the fucking door!
Open the door!
(PANTING)
Did you make it?
Yeah.
Where are we?
I don't know!
Fuck.
They froze the check.
What are we talking about here?
The payment for Ray's services.
They froze the check.
It's not frozen.
it's on hold. All right?
It's very common in
a $2.5 million transaction.
No. Common would be a week.
maybe 10 days.
This has been
way longer than that.
Jesus. Abby.
It's the federal government.
You know how they work.
Did you call that woman?
Yeah. I called.
Everything is fine.
Then where is he?
He is on the job
that he was hired to do.
So you're saying it's all good?
It's all good.
Where was the breach?
The auxiliary ballast tank
system on the starboard side.
Compartments five and seven
have been compromised.
And that leads to the ventilation
shaft under box two.
Portos.
(INDISTINCT RADIO CHATTER)
Yeah. they're full of rust.
Water pressure must have
snapped them clean off.
Maybe.
HOBBES: Portos isn't his name. is it?
Why wasn't I alerted?
CLARK: Look. it's like this. There's
a lot of people paying money
to make sure that
facility is unbreakable.
It's Ray Breslin.
The great Ray Breslin.
He's there to prove that
not even he can get out.
You make sure he stays there forever.
Do you have a problem with that?
No. Not at all.
Just the opposite.
Fucker.
All right. good.
There's one more thing.
The Chinese banks have joined
the Brazilians. the Russians.
the English. the U.S.
and the Swiss banks.
They're all paying to find out the
whereabouts of this Manheim fellow.
Word on the street is that
he has developed a program
to turn the entire world banking
system into fucking confetti.
Rottmayer worked with that asshole.
He knows where he is.
Your job is to get that
information out of him.
Well. it just so
happens that since Breslin
has gotten closer to Rottmayer.
Rottmayer has
developed a new edge
to his defiance that
wasn't there before.
I think Breslin is to blame.
Then break Breslin.
Thank you.
(HANGS UP)
I have an assignment
I know you'll enjoy.
(CHUCKLING)
(TAPPING)
Get on your feet!
(SCREAMING)
Wakey. wakey...
(MUFFLED GRUNTING)
Talk to me.
Come on. You must fight.
Get up!
Stay on your feet!
If we're on a ship.
we would know.
No.
Not if it was 1.000 feet long.
200 feet high.
with stabilizers.
We wouldn't know a damn thing.
Wakey. wakey!
Get him on his feet.
ROTTMAYER: You can do it. Keep going.
Come on. go. Move it!
We can't get out of here.
Yes. we can.
No!
(GROANING)
Get on your feet!
You've got to stay strong.
Back up! Back up!
It's you I want. Move it!
Ah!
Piece of shit...
(GROANING)
HOBBES: Stop it now. Drake.
Don't give up.
Don't let them break you.
What made you want to spend
your life in prison?
Hmm?
Tell me. What made you do it?
Tell me!
I was a lawyer. Prosecutor.
A man I put away
made a promise to me.
This man thought about that promise
every day for three years.
planning his way out of prison.
planning on how
he was gonna keep his word.
Taking a man's life is nothing.
Taking his heart...
That's everything. isn't it?
Everything.
RAY: You see. putting people
in prison wasn't good enough.
And I had to... I wanted to
make sure they stayed in
there. didn't get out.
I understand.
I have a daughter.
Never forget them.
You have a choice.
You can die in here.
or you can get out with me
and punish who put you here.
You hear me?
Yeah.
HUSH: Good news and bad news.
I was thinking about that first
meeting. privatized incarceration.
Off the grid. international profile.
And I started digging.
Code name. The Tomb. Completely
for profit. totally illegal.
Run by ex-military assholes and
Blackwater rejects. You know. bad dudes.
If Ray is anywhere. it's here.
Where is "here"?
That's the bad news.
I don't know.
No access to any layout.
No blind times.
We're in the middle
of the fucking ocean.
But I'll be damned
if I didn't find a routine.
RAY: They scramble the guard
shifts so they're never the same.
But they can't change the routine
of the guards themselves.
We don't know when they start.
We don't know when they end.
But I do know where they're
gonna be based on habit.
See that guy
coming down the stairs?
See how he walks
all pigeon-toed?
The Duck.
Yeah. The Duck
always works with the guy
scratching the back
of his neck.
ROTTMAYER: Hives.
Yeah. Hives.
When Duck and Hives work together.
they always do a circle.
They may do it at
random times of day.
It doesn't matter
when they do it.
it always ends up being 128
strides. then they split up. Watch.
Now they each take a side.
Duck walks 63 strides.
Hives 65.
Then they meet up at the top.
The guard down there
at the bottom.
the heavy-set guy.
he doesn't move much.
My guess is he's
been here a while
and only does
what he has to do.
Louisa.
Louisa?
His fat ass reminds me
of my first girlfriend.
Nice.
RAY: That guard over there
could be a problem for us.
He's always looking around.
The Chicken Man.
Chicken Man. right.
My guess. Chickie's new here.
Does everything by the book.
How do you know when the shift ends?
I don't.
But around this time. your girlfriend
Louisa starts looking at her watch.
My guess. it's lunchtime.
Welcome back.
Thanks.
Now that we've got the routine.
we just gotta ask the good
doctor where the hell we are.
DR. KYRIE: I'm not permitted to
give you anything for the pain.
so don't request it.
You're a doctor.
You took an oath.
"According to my ability
and judgment."
"I'll protect my patients
from harm and injustice."
What you're
doing here is wrong.
What exactly is it
you want from me?
I want to know
where the hell I am.
(YELPS)
Guards!
(GROANING)
It's okay.
It's under control.
Put him back here.
Sorry.
(DOOR BUZZES)
(GRUNTS)
So...
No.
Got to push him harder.
Push him. we'll lose him.
No other options?
Plan B.
You always gotta have a Plan B.
Did you get it?
Now I need his glasses.
Sir? You want
to take a look at this?
What's this?
It's a sextant.
Of course it is.
It works. You spot the North
Star with the horizon.
But it will only give
us half of our location.
Bring Breslin.
I'll explain how
it works later.
but first we've got
to get it topside.
Watch out.
Ah!
HOBBES: Welcome to your
new home. Mr. Breslin.
Section E.
Waiting for inmates.
You know who I am?
I do now.
I've studied your work very closely.
It's quite brilliant.
As a matter of fact.
it's what I used
as a reference guide
in designing this facility.
If you know who I am.
let me go.
No. no. no. no.
Mr. Breslin.
That's not how this works.
Not this time.
You see. the people who paid for you
to be here want you here forever.
And knowing that.
and knowing who you are.
well. who you were...
I can't have you communicating
with Rottmayer.
or anybody else.
for that matter.
This is the reality.
And there's no way out.
This can go two ways.
You let me go and I'll
pretend this never happened.
You don't. and I'll burn this fucking
place to the ground on my way out.
Effective right now.
no mess. no rec time.
and no showers.
I can get you Victor Manheim.
Rottmayer trusts me.
So you say.
Not good enough.
What have you got to lose?
Finding him has got to be worth
a lot more than what you were
paid for me. right. Hobbes?
It's a nice idea. but
as it stands right now.
I'm in line to get both.
You'll never break Rottmayer.
He'll die before he turns.
I'm your only chance
to get what you want.
I want Manheim and his whole network.
Names. Locations in real time.
Get that. If it checks out.
I'll let you go. But know this.
You tell me every word
that you and Rottmayer share.
or I will personally pull
the fucking life out of you.
Fair enough.
So what happened?
I'm playing you.
Last night Rottmayer told me
he started his network
with five guys
from his hometown.
He said he could trust
his life to these guys.
RAY: Give Javed the sextant.
Show him how to use it. Tell him
it's his ticket outta here.
Javed.
He'd rather see us dead.
He'll be the last one
they suspect.
He bragged how his network caused the
bank collapse in Iceland six years ago.
I don't give a shit
about six years ago.
I want to know where he is now.
You want to die?
You want to get out?
(SNAPS FINGERS)
Today.
They're plotting an escape.
An escape?
Really? Who and when?
I don't know all the details.
Just some.
Well. tell me
the details you know.
Hmm.
You give me things first.
Mr. Alfredo. Afridi. or whatever
the fuck your name is...
Your opium drug cartel friends have
paid a lot of money for you to be here.
(LAUGHING)
Of course they did.
those fucks.
So aside from your freedom.
what else can I give you?
I want the guards
to leave my people alone.
The Holy Koran...
I want one in my cell.
And I want to say
the name of Allah
and the prophet Mohammed
in the open air.
I want to be seen by my God
when I say my evening prayers.
That's all?
That's all.
I want to be seen
by my God. Mr. Hobbes!
(HELICOPTERS WHIRRING)
(SPEAKING IN ARABIC)
(MUTTERING)
30 degrees. 22 minutes.
We're in Horse Latitudes.
calm water.
North or south?
Water goes counter-clockwise above
the equator. so we're north.
How do we get the longitude?
They brought a new fish in yesterday.
He said it was November 20th.
We've got warm rain.
warm air at sea in November.
Now. you're building
a secret facility.
You're putting it on the water.
You're at 30 degrees
north latitude
because you want
to avoid rough water.
So you're going to want to stay away
from the Caribbean and the Pacific.
say. east of the China Sea.
If I was a betting man. I'd say we
could be off the coast of Morocco.
It's just a guess.
International waters.
Calm sea.
Close enough to land for supplies.
Educated guess.
I know a guy in Casablanca.
He owes me big-time.
Enough to come and get you?
He'd still owe me.
There's only one way to get
a message out. One way.
(CHOKING)
My God...
What is this?
You swallowed clotting powder?
Listen to me. I know you
think I'm playing you.
In Hobbes' office is a book.
Compromising Correctional Institution
Security by Ray Breslin.
On page 88 is a
detailed description
of Cell Block C at
Lewisburg Federal Prison.
Guards!
Check it out.
And remember your oath.
(GROANS)
I can't stall Hobbes anymore.
I've got to give him a location.
But we still don't have a plan.
It's in the doctor's hands.
(DOOR BUZZING)
MAN ON PA: Medical personnel.
Interrogation Three.
Medical personnel.
Guards!
Bring me prisoner Portos
from E Block.
Hobbes' orders. Do it now.
(EXHALES)
DR. KYRIE: Breathe in.
Again.
I saw the book.
How did you know?
I'm Ray Breslin.
I wrote the book.
Doctors are men who prescribe
medicines of which they know little
to cure diseases
of which they know less
for men of whom
they know nothing at all.
What do you want me to do?
The doctor is in.
Now Javed has to do his part.
Manheim's main base of operations
is 20 miles outside of Ruse.
That's on
the Bulgarian-Romanian border.
See?
Ratting out your
friends ain't so hard.
We've got 24 hours
before Hobbes realizes
the Bulgarian
location is bullshit.
Who do you know in C Block?
They've given permission
for your midnight prayer.
so what do you have for me?
Lock in on Breslin.
Yes. sir.
What are we up to?
Louder.
Louder. Louder!
(TAPPING) Got you.
HOBBES: Decode it.
Stop.
Zoom in.
It's Makmar Hassan.
Breslin is gonna have Hassan start
the break from Cell Block C.
We have a time frame.
And we have a location.
Cell Block C.
Triple the guard force there. I want
to know everyone who's involved.
You will. sir.
(SIREN WAILING)
MAN ON PA: Cell Block C.
prepare for inspection.
Cell Block C.
Louisa and Chicken Man. They sent
everyone else to Cell Block C.
You better be fuckin' right.
Don't worry.
Hey! You fucking
white trash scumbag bitch!
Where are you going. you fucking
towel-head al-Qaeda faggot?
Hey. your fuckin' sister gives...
Fuck you. you diaper-head...
You fuckin' skinhead!
You motherfuckin'...
(ALL CLAMORING)
The break was never
happening in Block C.
All men from C to Babylon.
Right now.
(GRUNTING)
Come on!
Argh!
(GRUNTS)
Come on!
DRAKE: Where the fuck
is Breslin?
Go. go. go! Let's move!
We've got 11 minutes
to get topside.
Let's hope
the doc made contact.
(WHISPERS) Go. Go.
What are you doing?
All the cameras are connected.
We've gotta block 'em out.
Sir!
Say "cheese."
Come on.
Okay. All right.
this is it. Let's go.
Engage security protocol five.
COMPUTER: Lockdown procedure engaged.
Lockdown procedure engaged.
It's a full lockdown.
We're all locked inside.
Eight minutes.
HOBBES: They're out of moves.
Drake. take two units. Drag
the rats back to their cages.
(HELICOPTER WHIRRING)
Hold up.
(GRUNTS)
Javed!
Open gate three! Take 'em!
(SIREN BLARING)
Go. go. go. go!
Don't fucking lose them!
Breslin!
DRAKE: Breslin! Open before I
break you. you motherfucker!
You'll never get out
of here alive. you arsehole!
We're gonna kill you!
We've gotta move!
(SHIVERING)
Smash that door down. I'll come
around from the other side.
Breslin. how the hell
do they know where we are?
You turned off
the cameras. right?
Motion detector.
Sir!
Out.
HOBBES: You can play your
games all day. Mr. Breslin.
but I'm still in control.
Whatever you do.
I have the power.
I own your ass.
You guys have gotta
get up that ladder.
I've got to find the engine room
and shut the power grid down.
Those magnetic locks
will stay open for about
five seconds before the
back-up generator kicks in.
You understand? That's all
the time you're gonna have.
Take this. Take it.
You're a good man.
Go do it.
What about you?
I'll be right behind you.
What if you're not
on the deck at 5:00?
Do what you've got to do.
There's always Plan B.
Come on. Let's do it.
We're dead men.
There's no way out.
Come with me. I won't
make it up that ladder.
I'll carry you up the ladder.
But I can hold them back.
No. I can carry
you up the ladder.
I'm not gonna leave you behind.
Give me your gun.
Just give me your gun.
Allah be with you.
I'll see you up there.
Now go.
Take care.
(PILOT SPEAKING)
Fuck!
Report?
JAVED: Fuck you.
you motherfucker!
We're taking gunfire
on the lower deck!
If he made it to the lower deck.
he's going to the engine room.
HOBBES: Meet me in the engine room.
I'm coming down.
Copy.
Get that fucker out of there!
Yes. sir.
Clear!
(JAVED MUTTERING IN ARABIC)
(GROANS)
(SPEAKING ARABIC)
Yeah. Whatever.
(FIRES GUN)
(GRUNTING)
Having trouble breathing?
(BOTH GRUNTING)
I'm gonna fucking
kill ya. motherfucker!
(YELPS)
Back off!
(BONES CRACKING)
MAN ON RADIO: Did you see him?
Yeah. he's here.
We're on our way...
I'll take care of it.
No. wait. wait!
(GROANS)
(MACHINES POWERING DOWN)
(COMPUTER BEEPING)
He's still on port. sir.
(HELICOPTER WHIRRING)
What the fuck?
Go! Get down!
We have a situation up here!
Fuck!
(GRUNTING)
Go low!
Go. go!
Plan B.
No one gets off this ship.
Shoot to kill.
Ah!
(SHOUTING INAUDIBLY)
Go. go!
Ah!
We have to go now!
Not yet!
(SHOUTING INAUDIBLY)
(ALL SCREAMING)
Give yourself up.
Mr. Breslin.
You can run around.
make some noise...
Spill some blood.
You can't get out.
Not really...
I know about
your wife. your son.
Aw.
I know every detail.
So thank you for pointing out all
the small flaws in my creation.
I'll be sure to fortify them.
But your time's up.
You hear me?
Breslin?
Your time is up.
(GUN FIRING)
(INAUDIBLE)
No one in. No one out. Search
every inch of this fucking room.
And power this thing back up!
GUARD: Come on!
Let's go. let's go!
(COMPUTER BEEPING)
Let's roll!
Go!
Argh!
Breslin!
Go down!
Come on. let's go!
Down. down!
We're gonna have to back off!
(ALARM BLARING)
(SHOUTING INDISCERNIBLY)
Rottmayer! Gun!
Gun!
Give me your gun!
(ALL GRUNTING)
(GROANING)
Boom.
Hmm.
Have a lovely day. asshole!
Now what?
Relax.
ROTTMAYER: You met her before.
Jessica Mayer.
It's an honor to meet you.
Your work is the gold
standard in the field.
She has been my eyes and
ears inside the Agency.
Hello. Dad.
And she's also my daughter.
Hello. darling.
JESSICA: Thank God
you made it.
ROTTMAYER: I missed you.
What happened?
Oh. nothing.
Don't worry about it.
You're Manheim.
Didn't see that coming.
You should've.
Yeah.
How'd you do it?
We have code names.
Code name Rottmayer meant
maximum security incarceration.
When my dad was picked up.
it activated the code.
And that's when
you called Les Clark.
I needed the best.
And after you agreed to do it.
I used my contacts deep
inside the DHS to get you in.
And the name you
gave me was the I.D. code.
HOBBES: Portos.
Rottmayer. Emil Rottmayer.
And I became your best friend.
You are not user-friendly.
I had to work very hard.
And that damn box.
That was hot.
It did get warm. yeah.
But it doesn't matter. What matters
is that I'm out and so are you.
We both served enough time.
You want to try it again?
(CHUCKLING)
You son-of-a-bitch...
I hope I never see you again.
That hurts.
One more thing!
How much did Les really know?
Only what I told him. at first.
But the next thing I know.
he's gone around me
and offered his services
to the backers of The Tomb.
So he knew where
I was being sent?
He arranged your transport.
ROTTMAYER: Need a ride?
No. thanks.
I made my own arrangements.
ABIGAIL: Wasn't tracking. We
knew something wasn't right.
Red flags going up
all over the place.
Clark was too calm about it.
so we started digging.
We found out he'd been
offered the CEO job
of running
the whole Tomb program
if the prototype you were
buried in proved inescapable.
At a salary of $5 million a
year. plus stock options.
Tell me you tracked him down.
Just like you asked. The
plan's in motion as we speak.
(ELEVATOR DINGS)
(CAR ALARM BEEPS)
It's sleepy-time.
motherfucker.
(PANTING)
(BEEPS)
Oh. fuck!
(CAR ENGINE STALLING)
No. no... Come on.
come on. come on...
Fuck!
Ray!
(SHIP HORN TOOTING)
(CELL PHONE RINGS)
It's Hush.
What did he say?
It's all good.
Good.
What's that?
Job offers.
Maybe later. Why don't you and
me have a very special dinner.
I'll cook.
Haven't I suffered enough?
(LAUGHING)